<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>K. 303-5. Pillar at Bakan level of Prasat Angkor Wat (IMA 10), 1549 Śaka</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
               <persName ref="part:kuch">
                  <forename>Kunthea</forename>
                  <surname>Chhom</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
               <persName>
                  <forename></forename>
                  <surname></surname>
               </persName>
               
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Siem Reap</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSCIK00303-5</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Kunthea Chhom.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
            <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                  <idno/>
                  <!-- don't modify this -->
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
                  <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
                  <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <p>The lettering is characteristic of the seventeenth century CE.                        <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. --></p>
                     <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
						<summary><p><p/></summary>
						<handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
						<handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
					 -->
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <schemaRef type="guide" key="EGDv01" url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="bib" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
               <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="part" matchPattern="([a-z]+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
               <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:kuch" when="2026-06-27" status="draft">Initial encoding of the inscription</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
                <div type="edition" xml:lang="okz-Latn" rendition="class:83231 maturity:83213">
                   <p>
   <lb n="1"/>sabbhamastu maṅgalātireka 1549 sakkha thoḥ qnakakhsatta khaeha māgha
                      <lb n="2"/>1 roja thṅaiya Āditya bārasaranā qnaka Ūdeyapuñā māna citta sā-
                      <lb n="3"/>thā nāṁ.m mepā poṅa phUna kūna cova moka Aṁmbī sruka jralaṅa mo- <!-- kuch: nāṁ.m -->
                      <lb n="4"/>ka kata doṅa satpakara dāṁṅa 7 heya chloṅa phnūsa phoṅa sota qnaka
                      <lb n="5"/>Ūdeyapuñā cova soma jūya Anamodanā jā prāka slīṅa 1 me Appa jūya
                      <lb n="6"/>slīṅa 1 me suka sliṅa 1 qnaka nai sliṅa 3 me ksūka slă 2 me mā
                      <lb n="7"/>sliṅa 2 Ā vara bhvīṅa 1 me braḥ sliṅa 2 qnaka pañāsādhāmma pāda 1
                      <lb n="8"/>qnaka Ūdaipañā pāda 3 sliṅa 3 neḥ jā rantāppa E kūsala phala pūnya sūma Isa dāṁṅa neḥ pāna citta lūḥ trībitta saṁmpāta kaṁmpī va-
                      <lb n="9"/>ṅvaeṅa dova keta nā caturāpāya nārraka ṭala mtoṅa sūma ltoḥ
                      <lb n="10"/>Aṁmbīya bhaiya caturāpāyabhuma nārraka noḥ sūma dova keta nā 
                      <lb n="11"/>solassabhāvakabraṁhma nāya hoṅa sūma khñuṁma pāna soya phala Ā-
                      <lb n="12"/>nisaṅa neḥ crena hoṅa caṁrena ñātīkā dāṁṅa 7 sāntāna mā-
                      <lb n="13"/>na dhāba Ita dhāba Oya pāna saṁmpata bimāna traiỵtrīṅa nāya 
                      <lb n="14"/>hoṅa neḥ lāyataiya jī naiya sāṅa du[[ka]] jā kīla
                      <lb n="15"/>mūya nī sota qnaka Ūdaipuñā sūma khñuṁ dova keta nāha
                      <lb n="16"/>sūrgga nāya Oya pāna saṁmpāta nibvāna jā sṭhāna khsaema Oya
                      <lb n="17"/>laeṅa Ambīya caturāpāyabhūma nārraka khñuṁ sūma māna bvoja
                      <lb n="18"/>Āhāra parabhogga kaṁmpī teca leya khñuṁ sūma sambata slaeka 
                      <lb n="19"/>kaṁmpī teca leya khñuṁ pqeha jā grāhāsa khñ[[u]]ṁma sūma māna
                      <lb n="20"/>śrīyaratta noḥ lqaha tūca nova cittra prāthnā naeḥ hoṅa
                      </p>
</div>
 <!-- <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                   <app loc="3">
                  <lem></lem>
                   <rdg source="bib:Lewitz1972_02"></rdg>
                   </app>
                   </listApp>  
         </div> -->
           <div type="translation" source="bib:Lewitz1972_02">
 	<p n="1-4">Que la prospérité soit! Immense Félicité! En 1549 Śaka, année du Lièvre, le dimanche, premier jour de la lune décroissante de mãgh, le vénérable Udayapaññā, rempli de foi, a amené ses parents, frères et sœurs et descendants du village de Jralaṅ (pour accomplir les œuvres suivantes). Ils coupèrent les sept oriflammes de l'Abhidhamma, puis firent entrer (des gens) en religion.</p>
              <p n="4-8">Cau Som, avec pieuse joie, offrit 1 sliṅ d'argent, me Ap 1 sliṅ, me Sukh 1 sliṅ, anak Mai 3 sliṅ, me Ksuk 2 sliṅ, me Mā 2 sliṅ, ā Var 1 hvīoeṅ, me Braḥ 2 sliṅ, le vénérable Pañnāsudhamm 1 pād, le vénérable Udayapaññā 3 pād 3 sliṅ : voilà les contributions d'offrandes.</p>
              <p n="8-11">Comme fruit de ces actes de mérite, il est souhaité que toutes ces personnes acquièrent la Triple Fortune! Que pas une seule fois elles ne s'égarent vers les quatre domaines de la souffrance et les enfers! Qu'elles soient délivrées du danger de ces endroits! Qu'elles aillent renaitre là-haut au bhavagga parmi les seize étages (du rūpabrahmaloka).</p>
              <p n="11-13">Puissé-je (déclare le vénérable Udayapaññā), jouir en abondance de l'avantage de ces mérites! Que tous mes parents des sept générations, riches ou pauvres, en profitent pour acquérir des palais célestes au Ciel des 'Trente-trois là-haut!</p>
              <p n="14">inseription sur pilier est l'œuvre de jī Nai.</p>
              <p n="15-20">Le vénérable Udayapaññā fit d'autre part le vœu (suivant) : "Puissé-je renaitre au Paradis, obtenir la Fortune du nirvāṇa, endroit de paix! Puissé-je échapper aux quatre domaines de la souffrance et aux enfers! Puissé-je obtenir continuellement de la nourriture et des "sampot" (ou étoffes) pour me couvrir! Serais-je maître de maison, je souhaiterais obtenir les meilleures des femmes, les plus belles que puisse souhaiter mon cœur! »</p>
                                 </div> 
           <!-- <div type="commentary">
           <p></p>
         </div> -->
        <div type="bibliography">
          <p>Edited by Saveros Lewitz (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Lewitz1972_02"/><citedRange unit="page">221-224</citedRange></bibl>) with a French translation. Re-edited here by Kunthea Chhom based on EFEO estampage n. 73.</p>
	 <listBibl type="primary">
             <bibl n="SL">
             <ptr target="bib:Lewitz1972_02"/>
             <citedRange unit="page">221-224</citedRange>
                 </bibl>
             </listBibl>
           <listBibl type="secondary">
             <bibl n="EA">
      <ptr target="bib:Aymonier1900_02"/><citedRange unit="page">143-175</citedRange>
    </bibl>
              <bibl n="MK">
      <ptr target="bib:Krassem1984_01"/><citedRange unit="page">29-30</citedRange>
    </bibl>
              </listBibl>
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
